http://youtu.be/lJu8XWjqffE
Tung Dinh http://youtu.be/lJu8XWjqffE
PROFESSOR: So we looked at finite state machines.
Ta đã biết về máy trạng thái hữu hạn
Now we have to see how we can convert a finite state
Giờ ta tìm hiểu cách chuyển máy trạng thái hữu hạn
machine from an abstraction, which is a state transition graph,
từ thí thuyết là đồ thị chuyển trạng thái
to code, which is my software.
đến code, là software
In order to do that, I have to build some concept-- built up
Để làm được, ta phải tạo vài định nghĩa
on some concept.
on some concept.
And the concept we're going to build in programming is what is called a struct.
gọi là Struct
A struct is-- the definition would be, for a struct,
1 Struct là
would be that it's a mechanism to store composite information.
cơ chế lưu trữ thông tin tổng tợp
It's a composite store.
It's a composite store.
Now, because it's allowing us to store composite information,
Bởi nó cho phép lưu thông tin tổng hợp
we will also call it-- it's a user defined-- as a user defined type.
người dùng có thể dịnh dạng loại được
Now, we've already seen a composite store.
Ta cũng đã biết về bộ lưu tổng hợp
An array is a composite store.
ví dụ như là 1 array
What an array allows us to do is store a set of items in consecutive locations.
Array cho phép lưu 1 chuỗi thông tin liên tiếp
And that the key thing in an array is all these items
Và quan trọng là mọi phần tử trong array
have to be of the same type.
phải thuộc cùng kiểu dữ liệu
So a struct, on the other hand, is a composite store
1 Struct, nói cách khác, là bộ lưu tổng hợp
where the items can be of dissimilar type.
mà các phần tử có thể thuộc nhiều kiểu dữ liệu khác nhau
They don't have to all be of the same type.
Chúng không cần giống kiểu dữ liệu
So this is important to us in finite state machines
Nó rất quan trọng trong máy trạng thái hữu hạn
because we want to capture all the information about the finite state
bởi ta muốn nắm tất cả thông tin về
machine.
máy trạng thái hữu hạn
We want to capture states.
Ta cần nắm các trạng thái
We want to capture inputs.
inputs
We want to capture outputs.
outputs
And they may not all be of the same type.
Và chúng có thể không cùng kiểu dữ liệu
Some might be two bits.
Một số có thể 2 bits
Some might be a string.
số khác có thể là 1 chuỗi
One might be something else.
cũng có thể là kiểu khác
And states are indexes, and so on.
Và trạng thái là chỉ số, vân vân
So what we want is a new concept.
Cái ta cần là 1 định nghĩa mới
And the concept is a struct.
Và nó là 1 struct
So let's try to understand this by taking some real example.
Để hiểu rõ hơn thì ta có 1 ví dụ thực tế
Let's say we were working on a game.
Giả sử ta đang làm game
So let's have a game.
đây, 1 game
And in this game-- and this is a screen of my game.
Trong game này, đây là màn hình game
And in this game, I have a player.
ta có 1 player
So let's say there's a player in this.
Đây, 1 player trong game
And this player has certain attributes.
Và player này có vài thuộc tính nhất định
So for example, this player is within this two dimensional space.
ví dụ, player này trong không gian 2D
This player is currently at this point.
player này hiện tại đang ở điểm này
So I want to store all the information about this player.
Ta muốn lưu mọi thông tin về player này
So what I do is I say, OK, I have a player,
So what I do is I say, OK, I have a player,
and I want to store information about this player.
and I want to store information about this player.
What information do I want to store?
Thông tin gì ta cần lưu
Well, I say this is a player.
Ta có 1 player
And he's a new type-- he's not-- he's not an integer.
và nó là 1 kiểu mới, nó không phải là 1 integer
He's not a long.
cũng chẳng phải 1 long
He's not a short.
không phải 1 short
He's not a character.
không là 1 character
He's not a string.
không là 1 string
He's not even an array.
cũng không là 1 array
He is a new type.
mà là 1 dạng mới
So I'll call it a struct.
gọi là struct
And I'm going to list all the attributes that display it has.
Và ta sẽ liệt kệ các thuộc tính nó có
Now for me, I'm going to keep it simple.
Để đơn giản
This player has three attributes.
ta cho player này có 3 thuộc tính
He has a position, which is-- let's say an unsigned char where his position is
nó có toạ độ, giả sử là unsigned char
where is he relative on the x-axis and on the y-axis.
biểu diễn trên trục x và trục y
So this is x-coordinate and this is y-coordinate.
Đây là trục x, còn đây là y
So I'm going to call this his x position and his y position.
Ta gọi đây là toạ độ x, còn đây là y
Now, it's possible that the x's define-- this might be my origin
đây có thể là gốc toạ độ
and that's why that's x and y.
và đây là x và y
Or this could be an origin in which case x and y have different meanings.
Hoặc đây có thể là toạ độ, thì x và y sẽ là khác
But it doesn't really matter.
Nhưng nó không quan trọng
So what I also have with respect to this player is maybe I store his score.
Cái ta cũng cần lưu về player này là điểm số
So I have an unsigned, another unsigned, maybe a short
Ta đã có unsigned, unsigned nữa, có thể là 1 short
which tell me what his points are, how many points
cho ta biết điểm số player là bao nhiêu
he has at this particular point in time.
Nó có điểm tại thời điểm nào đó
So maybe those are my three attributes.
Đó là 3 thuộc tính
So I define that.
ta xác định
And this I will end with a semicolon.
Và kết thúc bằng chấm phẩy ";"
So this defines a new type called player.
Đây là kiểu dữ liệu mới, gọi là player
Now, if I want to, I can now do this, which is I can say typedef.
Bây giờ, nếu ta muốn, có thể làm thế này, gõ typedef
I'm defining a new type called a player type.
Ta định nghĩa 1 kiểu dữ liệu mới gọi là player
So this struct player which I just described up here
Cái struct player mà tôi vừa mô tả trên kia
is going to be from here onwards, I'm going to call him a PType.
sẽ chuyển từ trên kia xuống, ta gọi nó là PType
And so, what this allows me is the convenience of declaring-- so
Và nó dễ dàng hơn để định nghĩa
for example, PType, I can say P1, player one, is a PType.
ví dụ, PType P1, player 1, là dạng PType
Which when I make this declaration, in memory then, there will be space
Khi định nghĩa thế này, trong memory sẽ có 1 khoảng trống
allocated.
được cấp
There will be one character for where the x position will be stored.
Sẽ có 1 character về toạ độ x
Another so this is my P1.
Đây là P1
And P1 has the first attribute which is x position, the second attribute which
Và P1 có thuộc tính đầu tiên, là toạ độ x, cái thứ hai
is a y position, which are both one character, which is eight bits.
là toạ độ y, cả 2 đều à character, dài 8 bits
And then I have points which are two bytes.
Và rồi ta có điểm số, dài 2 bytes
So that's two bytes, one byte, one byte.
Vậy là 2 bytes, 1 byte, 1 byte
Because my points are two bytes long.
Bởi điểm số dài 2 bytes
So I can now declare a user, a particular player like that.
Giờ, ta có thể khai báo 1 người dùng, là 1 player như vậy
Now, if I want to set the player's position so this
Nếu ta muốn tạo toạ độ cho player
is my declaration, and somewhere in my code,
Đây là phần khai báo, còn phần khác trong code
let's say I want to set the position of this player to a particular point,
giả sử ta muốn tạo toạ độ cho player
so I can do this.
Ta có thể làm được
I can say, I want to take player one, and I want to change his attributes.
Để thay đổi thuộc tính player
So I use the dot operator.
ta dùng phép toán dot
to access the fields within-- attributes within a struct.
để truy xuất những thuộc tính trong 1 struct
So I say P1 dot-- that's the dot operator, which is just
Ta viết P1.xpos
the period-- x position equals, let's say I want to be at 45-- position 45.
toạ độ x bằng, giả sử là 45
And maybe my-- because it's a char, I know that the values that it can take
Bởi nó là 1 char, ta biết giá trị nó có thể chạy
is anywhere from zero to 255 because char is eight bits.
bất kể từ 0 đến 255, vì char có 8 bits
So maybe that's my x position.
Nên có lẽ đây là toạ độ x
And maybe I have a y position for him also.
và ta tạo toạ đọ y cho player luôn
So I set, let's say, his y position is equal to 50.
giả sử toạ độ y bằng 50
So that's how I can access and modify an attribute of a struct.
Đó là cách ta truy xuất và điều chỉnh thuộc tính của struct
And I can also do this, which is p1.points.
Và ta cũng có thể làm, P1.points
Maybe it's just started the code, and so his points are zero.
để bắt đầu code, thì giả sử là 0
So that's a way to initialize or set values.
Đó là cách khởi tạo chuỗi giá trị
Now, we can also-- if you know that we can define a single player like this,
Ta có thể khởi tạo từng player như vậy
we can also define an array of players.
cũng có thể khởi tạo 1 array players
Maybe as a part of my game, maybe what I have is a bunch of ships.
có thể là 1 phần trong game, ta có thể có một loạt tàu
These are, let's say, my enemy ships.
giả sử là tàu địch
And maybe I have an array of ships.
và ta có 1 array ships
Like I said, there are five ships.
gồm 5 tàu
So I can declare them like so.
Ta có thể định nghĩa chúng thế này
I can say, for example, PType-- again, I'm calling them player type,
ví dụ: PType, chúng cũng thuộc kiểu player
but they're a different kind of player-- an adversary if you will.
nhưng là dạng khác, là kẻ thù
And let's say they're called ships.
Ta gọi chúng là ships
And I can declare five of those ships.
Và ta khai báo có 5 ships
Now, if I do that, in memory then-- let's create some space here.
Nếu làm như vậy, trong memory, sẽ có vài khoảng trống
In memory then, I'm declaring not one player, but multiple players.
ta không khai báo 1 player, nhưng nhiều players
So this is multiple players.
So this is multiple players.
And so I have something called ships.
Và ta gọi khoảng trống này là ships
So this is, let's say, ships of zero.
đây là ships[0]
And zero itself will have three attributes in it.
và ships[0] có 3 thuộc tính
And then ships of one, which is a second ship, will have key attributes in it.
rồi tới ships[1], cũng có thuộc tính vậy
So I'm going to draw this line to kind of distinguish.
Và ta vẽ đường này để dễ phân biệt
And although we have two ships, before-- because remember,
Và mặc dù ta có 2 ships rồi, nhưng
our indexes go from 0 to 4.
số thứ tự chạy từ 0 đến 4
So this will also have three attributes in that.
Cái cuối này cũng có 3 thuộc tính
And they're continuously allocated.
và liên tiếp được phân bổ
So let's take a look at how we can use this idea of structures
Giờ thì xem cách để dùng strutures
and also to manipulate the position of the ships.
và điều khiển vị trí của tàu
So if you remember what we did was we said
Nếu bạn nhớ, ta đã nói,
we had the screen where we had ships that we
ta có 1 mằn hình, ta có tàu
wanted to-- there are five ships.
5 chiếc
There are five ships on the screen.
đây, 5 chiếc trên màn hình
And let's write a routine which will take one of these ships
Và giờ, ta viết 1 routine mà mang 1 con tàu
and move the ship to the center of my screen.
chuyển về giữa màn hình
And to do that, I have a subroutine that I'm going to write.
Để làm được, ta có 1 subroutine sẽ viết
The subroutine is called MoveCenter.
gọi là MoveCenter
And it's going to be passed the identity of the ship-- which
Và ta sẽ cho vào giá trị con tàu
ship I want to move.
mà ta muốn di chuyển
So I'm going to pass it long i, which is to indicate
Ta sẽ đưa vào, long i
that I'm passing the i-th ship is the one that I'm trying to move.
nghĩa là ta đưa thông số tàu thứ i vào để di chuyển
And since this subroutine doesn't return anything, it does some work.
Bởi subroutine không trả ra giá trị gì, nó chỉ làm thôi
It's not going to-- it's going to have a void.
nên ta viết void
So this subroutine-- first, it will take my array of ships which we looked at
Cái subroutine này, đầu tiên, lấy array ships
and extract the i-th ship from that array of ships,
và đưa ra ships[i] từ array
which is now a record, which is a structure.
là structure
And we know that we use a dot operator to access fields within this structure.
nên là dùng phép toàn dot để truy xuất giá trị trong structure
We'll make the x position be equal to 128 so that we move the ship's position
Ta thiết lập .xpos = 128 để di chuyển toạ độ x của tàu
to be an x value of 128 and also a y value of 128.
về 128 và .ypos = 128
That's it's new position.
Đó là toạ độ mới
So we set the x position, we set the y position,
Vậy ta đã thiết lập toạ độ x và y
and we also decided that every time it moves to the center,
Và ta thống nhất rằng mỗi khi nó đi tới vị trí giữa
maybe this was some step that it performed that got it an extra point.
ta có thêm điểm
So I'm going to take the ship's i.
Ta sẽ lấy ships[i]
I'm going to check its current points.
check xem điểm hiện tại
So I'll compare that against the maximum points possible.
và so sánh với điểm tối đa
So if it's still less than 65535-- because remember that the points
Vậy nếu nó thấp hơn 65535, bởi vì định dạng của points
field is an unsigned short and the largest unsigned short
là unsigned short, và nó là giá tri lớn nhất
So the max value we can have is 65535 with a short.
Vậy giá trị tối đa ta đạt được là 65535 cho 1 short
So I check against that bounds.
Rồi ta check với các giới hạn rào
And if it's well within the bounds, then I'm going to add 1 to its points.
Nếu nó đúng, ta sẽ cộng 1 vào points
I will add one to it kind of like this.
,points++
So a colon there.
rồi chấm phẩy ";"
I close that.
cuối cùng là đóng ngoặc lại
So this subroutine whenever it's called in
Khi được gọi, cái subroutine này
will modify the position of the ships, the i-th ship, in the game grid.
sẽ thay đổi vị trí của tàu thứ i trong game.